this is democracy now democracynow.org
the quarantine report
i'm amy goodman in new york joined by my
co-host juan gonzalez who's in new
brunswick new jersey
hi juan hi amy and welcome to all of our
listeners and viewers across the country
and around the world
well with less than 12 hours before the
end of his presidency
donald trump issued 143 pardons and
commutations including a pardon for
steve bannon
his former chief strategist and campaign
manager in august bannon was arrested
for defrauding trump supporters
who donated to a pro-wall anti-immigrant
non-profit called
we build the wall in recent weeks bannon
helped promote conspiracy theories about
the 2020 election and urged trump
supporters to come to washington d.c on
january 6
when rioters attacked the capitol in an
insurrection that left
five people dead including a capital
police officer
other high-profile pardons included
elliot broidy one of trump's top
fundraisers in 2016
and three former republican congressmen
rick renzi
robin hayes and randall duke cunningham
added to another several congressmen
early trump supporters that trump uh
gave commutations or pardons to
trump also gave a pardon to ken kersen a
close friend of jared kushner
trump's son-in-law carson is the former
editor of the new york observer who was
arrested in october for
cyber stalking three people including
his ex-wife
the rappers lil wayne and kodak black
also received pardons the white house
announced the latest pardon
shortly before 1 a.m this morning
trump had previously pardoned other top
associates including former campaign
manager paul manafort former national
security adviser michael flynn
advisor roger stone as well as jared
kushner's father
as well as four blackwater mercenaries
who massacred 17 iraqis in the 2007
nissor square massacre in baghdad iraq
trump has so far rejected calls to
pardon wikileaks founder julian assange
or nsa whistleblowers
edward snowden and reality winner
meanwhile trump pardoned israeli spy
aviamcella who was indicted in 1987 of
recruiting u.s naval intelligence
analyst jonathan
pollard to sell secrets to israel this
all comes as more details emerge about
how
allies of trump have personally profited
from people seeking pardons
the new york times reports an associate
of rudy giuliani told cia
torture whistleblower john kiriakou a
pardon is quote going to cost
2 million dollars kiriakou declined the
offer but he did pay 50 thousand dollars
to a former top trump campaign adviser
for help
in his quest to secure a pardon well to
talk more about the pardon system we are
joined by john kiriakou himself
who is still seeking a pardon kiriakou
served 23 months in prison after he
exposed the cia's torture program
john kiriakou welcome back to democracy
now before we get your response to these
pardons
tell your own story your own attempt to
get a pardon
and what it involved it was different
under uh donald trump than it was
certainly under barack obama the the
normal way of applying for a pardon is
you simply go online
to the website of the office of the us
pardon attorney you fill out the form
it then goes to the fbi which does an
investigation
and then the pardon attorney makes a
recommendation of yes or no
that's the way it's supposed to work the
way it worked under donald trump
is that he ignored the office of the u.s
pardon attorney
in most cases the pardon attorney wasn't
even consulted
if you were a friend of the president or
you knew someone who was a friend of the
president or
you hired a friend of the president and
you could get to him
i thought it was uh and make your case
then you were considered for a pardon
uh what i did was i had to hire a
lobbyist who
had uh headed the the trump campaign in
florida in 2016.
uh she charged me 50 000 that i didn't
have i had to borrow
with a promise of another 50 000 once i
got the pardon
the money went down the drain but we now
know that uh that other associates of
donald trump were charging
double that even 10 and 20 times that
and john kiriakou what about this issue
of uh
you're being told that rudy giuliani
could help win you a pardon for two
million dollars
who made the uh who told you that and
could you tell us any more about that
offer
sure i uh had a meeting with uh with
four other people that included rudy
giuliani
on july 1st of last year here in
washington at the trump hotel it was a
it was a meeting completely unrelated to
to a pardon and i
frankly didn't even intend to make the
request
but there was a lull in the conversation
so i thought i'd take advantage of the
opportunity
and so i said uh well mr mayor can we
talk about maybe asking for a
presidential pardon
he immediately said that he had to use
the men's room and he got up and he
walked away
one of his aides who was there at the
meeting then said to me
rudy doesn't talk about pardons you have
to talk to me
and he's going to ask you for two
million dollars and i laughed
and i said i don't have two million
dollars i said are you out of your mind
two million dollars why would i spend
two million dollars
to recover a 700 000 pension that
doesn't make any sense
and i dropped it but he said that that's
what the the price was
now they don't see this as a bribe they
don't see it as
buying a pardon they see it as as
lobbying
which is you know and a dirty thing that
happens in washington but this is the
way washington works
now supposedly trump uh saw you
on a fox news show that hosted by tucker
carlson and
uh could you talk about that
sure uh it was in october of 2019 i was
on the tucker carlson show
talking this is on fox news talking
about
um my my case that
i was i was prosecuted under barack
obama after i blew the whistle on the
cia's torture program
and uh and my real detractor uh in the
obama administration was john brennan
i said that robert mueller had set up
the john kiriakou task force
and that peter strzok had actually
arrested me
and i you know was looking for for a
pardon
well it turned out that donald trump was
watching the episode that night
and he called jared kushner and said
there's a guy
john kiriakou on fox news you should get
in touch with him
so the next day my attorney got a call
from jared kushner's attorney and a
couple days after that
we met in kushner's attorney's office
uh kushner was very cold
he was very stiff and not at all
friendly amiable open what he said was
what do you want and i said i want a
presidential pardon
and he said give me one page i want
three quarters of the page
explaining your your uh situation your
case your background
the other quarter of the page i want you
to tell me
how a pardon for you helps donald trump
get reelected
so i did what i could my attorney wrote
this one page
we sent it to kushner and never heard
anything again
now and how does that compare to what
the normal process is supposed to be for
someone seeking a presidential pardon
the normal process is you wouldn't even
know who jared kushner was
the the problem that we have here is
that
over the years the office of the us
pardon attorney
has seen it as its role to deny
people's applications for pardons if you
have 10 000
applications a year and you only make
recommendations for
five pardons or ten pardons then the
system is broken
and so trump recognized that the system
was broken and he also recognized that
he had unfettered authority to take care
of his friends
and his associates and that's what he
did uh he did it in a really
ugly uh unethical way
but he did it because really for his
friends
and associates there was no way around
it they weren't going to go to the
website of the pardon attorney and and
fill out a form they were going to go
directly to the president frankly what
we need
is a bipartisan effort to reform the
pardon process
first of all the pardon attorney should
not be housed at the justice department
it should be housed at the white house
secondly it should be independent
of the prosecutors at the justice
department and independent
of the attorney general and it's not and
so nothing gets done
you